So today we start on דף ט עמוד א, Daf Tet Amud
Aleph, see if we can catch up a little, the official דף
daf should be י, Yud, but okay, we're at 9a here at
the משנה, Mishnah, and here's what it says. We're talking about again
different types of חטאות, chataot, so we dealt with the category of
מחוסרי כפרה, mechusrei kapparah, a חטאת chatat is really coming for cleansing
and purification, and now we have a חטאת chatat which is a
sin offering but it is not but it has a different parameter.
So let's take a look. אלו מביאין על הזדון כשוגג. Eilu mevi'in
al hazadon kishogeg. The following bring for even willful sins just like
for for those that are unintentional. Normally a חטאת chatat is only
for an unintentional sin, but there are some, there are four that
you bring even if for intentional sins. What are they? הבא על
השפחה, Haba al hashifchah, somebody has sex with a female slave. The
גמרא, Gemara, the תורה Torah speaks about that a woman who is
about a שפחה, shifchah, והיא שפחה נחרפת לאיש, vehi shifchah necheret le'ish,
וחפשה לא ניתן לה, vechufshah lo nitan lah, that she
has not been fully freed. And the way חז"ל Chazal understand it
is that it's a שפחה shifchah that has somehow been sort of
half married to a slave, he's half free, half married, half not
free. So anyway there's some type of a quasi-marriage there, she's some
type of a quasi-married woman but she's not fully. And the תורה
Torah basically says that if a man sleeps with her, he gets
lashes and brings a קרבן korban even if it's intentional. A Jewish
man, yes. Now, the שפחה, shifchah, well again, it's not exactly clear
what the, here let me read you the פסוק, pasuk, it's not
exactly clear what the case the תורה Torah is describing, but the
way חז"ל Chazal understand it, I'm just trying to find the exact
פסוק, pasuk, the way חז"ל Chazal understand it, it is talking about
somebody that is, it's normally understood to be a woman who is
half slave, half free. So therefore the fact that she's married to
a man, it's not like a full binding marriage because she's not
fully free, but it's not like it's nothing either because she's also
she also is half free. So let me just see if I
can find the פסוק pasuk quickly.
We're on 9a.
Right, here, let me let me let me, no, it's back to
8b, here let me
read the פסוק. pasuk.
No, but do we recognize marriage between an עבד eved and a
שפחה?
shifchah? No, we don't. ואיש כי ישכב את אשה שכבת זרע, Ve'ish
ki yishkav et ishah shichvat zera, והיא שפחה נחרפת לאיש, vehi shifchah
necheret le'ish, so she is נחרפת necheret to a man, which somehow
means designated for another man, והפדה לא נפדתה או חפשה לא ניתן
לה, vehapdeh lo nifdetah o chufshah lo nitan lah, בקרת תהיה לא
יומתו כי לא חפשה.
bikoret
tihyeh
lo yumtu ki lo chufashah. She doesn't get, they don't get put
to death because she has not yet been fully freed, so her
marriage is not really fully binding. And what does he do? והביא
את אשמו לה' אל פתח אהל מועד איל אשם, vehevi et ashamo
l'Adonai el petach ohel moed eil asham,
וכפר עליו הכהן באיל האשם לפני ה' על חטאתו אשר חטא ונסלח
לו מחטאתו אשר חטא. vechiper alav hakohen be'eil ha'asham lifnei Adonai al
chatato asher chata venislach lo mechatato asher chata. So again, so it's
somehow some sense of half-married. So it's not that if it was
just with a שפחה shifchah which wasn't designated to a man or
so on, it would not be, I mean there's actually a question
is it a לאו lav or not, but anyway it would not
be this category, it would not be a קרבן. korban. If she
were freed it would be adultery, if it was a really binding
marriage, so it's this middle category.
Now, הבא על השפחה, Haba al hashifchah, so that's one. ונזיר שנטמא.
Venazir shenitma. If a נזיר nazir became טמא. tamei. A נזיר nazir
is not allowed to become טמא, tamei, but if he becomes טמא
tamei he brings special קרבנות, korbanot, and that's even if he becomes
טמא במזיד. tamei bemezid. ושבועת העדות. Ushvuat ha'edut. If somebody swears falsely
that he doesn't know testimony to somebody, even if it's an intentional
false oath, that is brings a קרבן, korban, we'll see how we
know all this in the גמרא. Gemara. ושבועת הפקדון. Ushvuat hapikadon. Similarly
if somebody takes an oath that to deny that he's that he's
the guardian of an object for somebody,
that also you bring a קרבן korban even if it's intentionally false,
and those are the four. So we'll analyze all those in the
גמרא. Gemara. חמשה מביאין קרבן אחד על עבירות הרבה. Chamishah mevi'in korban
echad al aveirot harbeh. Now we get to a different category, like
special. So normally we said that you only bring one קרבן korban
per sin, but there are five times that you can bring one
קרבן korban for many sins. וחמשה מביאין קרבן עולה ויורד, Vechamishah mevi'in
korban oleh veyored, and five times you bring a קרבן korban that
changes in value. These are not sort of thematically organized, right? So
because we're shifting from things that are about about purification and atonement
to things that are about sin to things, anyway but they're organized
by numbers. So first you have the four, right? Four that are
four that are about מחוסרי כפרה, mechusrei kapparah, about about purification, four
that are about whether you are intentional or unintentional. Then you have
five. Five that are about things that you can bring about about
about one קרבן korban for many sins, and also five that the
value changes. Okay, so these are all like special cases חטאות chataot
or אשמות, ashamot, but and they're being organized in terms of the
numbers. Okay? So there are five that you bring for that you
can bring for multiple sins, there are five that you bring that
base based on your economic ability the what you have to bring
changes in value. אלו מביאין קרבן אחד על עבירות הרבה. Eilu mevi'in
korban echad al aveirot harbeh. The following is the ones that you
bring one קרבן korban for many sins. הבא על השפחה ביאות הרבה,
Haba al hashifchah bi'ot harbeh, so the שפחה shifchah case again, if
it's many acts of sex, it's still nevertheless only one. one קרבן,
korban, and
a נזיר nazir that had that became טמא tamei many times, so
again that's similar to the previous category of things that you bring
even intentional, so at least the first two are like that, if
many times of sinning with one with one female with one female
slave, many times of becoming טמא, tamei, all of those is only
going to be one קרבן. korban. The problem is that it says
here five bring and it only listed two, right? It didn't list
five. So the next משנה mishna
is the you know is the list of the five. Okay let
me actually think it might be more than one
משנה. mishna. Yes, anyways the next משנה mishna completes the list of
the five. So the way the משניות mishnayot are broken down are
a little funny. Okay let's first talk about the four that are
for intentional as well as unintentional. הבא על שפחה מנלן? Haba al
shifcha minalan? How do you know this case about the שפחה shifcha
that it's even for intentional? תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: וכפר עליו הכהן
באיל האשם על חטאתו אשר חטא. Vechiper alav hakohen be'eil ha'asham al
chatato asher chata. For the sin that he has sinned. מלמד, Melamed,
so the fact that it says חטאתו אשר חטא chatato asher chata
is a little redundant, so first we teach us the end of
the משנה, mishna, שמביא קרבן אחד על עבירות הרבה. shemevi korban echad
al aveirot harbeh. You bring one קרבן korban for many sins, right?
Could have just said על חטאתו, al chatato, but the fact that
it mentions sin multiple times means even if the person has done
it multiple times, he only has to bring one offering. Okay now,
ונסלח לו מחטאתו אשר חטא, Venislach lo mechatato asher chata, it'll be
atoned for him
from the sin that he has sinned, so again that's a redundant
yet again, the sin that he has sinned, so what does that
tell you? לעשות שוגג כמזיד, La'asot shogeg kemezid, or really it's מזיד
כשוגג. mezid keshogeg. Even if you're intentional it's like you're unintentional. So
either way the sin offering because of the redundancy of חטאתו אשר
חטא chatato asher chata multiple times, the חז"ל Chazal understand that this
sin of the of the half-married שפחה, shifcha, number one you would
bring one קרבן korban for multiple times, but also you bring for
the whole range of sins whether intentional or unintentional. So that is
the issue about the שפחה. shifcha. Now, נזיר שנטמא, nazir shenitma, for
a נזיר nazir becoming טמא, tamei, even for an intentional בטומאה bitumah
you bring you bring a sin offering. מנלן? Minalan? Where do you
know this from? דכתיב: Dechtiv: וכי ימות מת עליו בפתע פתאום. Vechi
yamut met alav befeta pitom. If a dead person dies on him
suddenly. Okay that sounds like it's sort of like it was an
accident, a complete accident, maybe even an אונס. ones. So where are
we going to get מזיד mezid out of there? So let's take
a look. So פתע, peta, suddenly, זה שוגג. zeh shogeg. That that
you were unintentional. וכן הוא אומר, Vechein hu omer, and similarly the
verse says: אם בפתע בלא איבה הדפו. Im befeta belo eivah hadafo.
This is talking about somebody who accidentally killed somebody and it says
like if suddenly without like premeditation and
and enmity he he pushed him and he killed him. So פתע
peta means that it wasn't intentional, it was unintentional. So we're talking
about a נזיר nazir became טמא, tamei, it says פתע פתאום. peta
pitom. So normally you would think that underscores like it was
completely unanticipated, like it was completely nothing he could have controlled. But
we're going to explain that פתע peta means normal case of unintended,
which you learn out from other places, and פתאום pitom could mean
either completely uncontrolled like אונס ones or it could even mean intentional.
Let's take a look how we look at that how we see
that. פתאום זה אונס. Pitom zeh ones. So one thing פתאום pitom
can mean is completely you know completely uncontrolled,
completely against you know without any fault. וכן הוא אומר, Vechein hu
omer, similarly it says: ויאמר ה' פתאום אל משה. Vayomer Hashem pitom
el Moshe. God said suddenly to Moshe. And obviously when God comes
to speak to Moshe, it's nothing Moshe can control, it's something that
the it's completely the circumstances outside of you that all of a
sudden you know came upon you. So one sense and that's פשט
pshat of פתאום pitom means like it's completely something just happened to
you. Okay but but תניא אידך, tanya idach, we taught in another
braita, פתאום זה מזיד. pitom zeh mezid. פתאום pitom means the exact
opposite, intentional. Where do you get the idea that פתאום pitom means
intentional? וכן הוא אומר: Vechein hu omer: ערום ראה רעה ונסתר ופתאים
עברו ונענשו. Arum ra'ah ra'ah venistar ufetayim avru vena'anashu. A sly person
sees evil can anticipate bad things and hides himself, ופתאים, ufetayim,
now the word isn't פתאום, pitom, the word is פתאים, petayim, foolish
people עברו ונענשו, avru vena'anashu, they transgress and are punished. So the
דרשה drasha is
פתאים petayim and פתאום, pitom, פתאום pitom is
can also mean a willful transgression.
Usually the ערום arom is a bad guy.
I know, but yeah in משלי Mishlei ערום arom sometimes just means
the sort of the you know sort of a
not bad, but the just the the sly person or right the
intelligent person right. Anyway moving on. Okay. נכתוב
קרא, Nichtov kra, so the גמרא gemara says if פתאום pitom means
both ends of the of the spectrum, then נכתוב קרא פתאום, nichtov
kra pitom, just say פתאום, pitom, דמשמע שוגג ומשמע מזיד ומשמע אונס.
demashma shogeg u'mashma mezid u'mashma ones. Now maybe פתאום pitom means everything,
maybe it not only means אונס ones and מזיד, mezid, maybe it
even שוגג. shogeg. How do we know it means שוגג, shogeg, which
is like negligent, it's not complete an accident but it's not
intentional? דכתיב, Dechtiv, as the verse says,
פתע. peta. It’s not like it’s completely just an accident happened to
you, you know, or like some people anyway say accidents don’t just
happen. But okay, anyway, so if you’re a little bit too gullible,
you’re also a little bit to blame. So anyway, that’s like a
שוגג. shogeg. So why didn’t it just say פתאום? pitom? That means
the entire spectrum. So לא נכתוב קרא פתא. lo nichtav kra pesa.
So the Gemara says
no, אי כתב קרא פתאום, ei kasav kra pitom, הוה משמע שוגג,
hava mashma shogeg, on the one hand it can mean negligent, ומשמע
מזיד ומשמע אונס, u-mashma meizid u-mashma ones, it could also mean intentional
and completely accident. הוה אמינא, hava amina, I would have thought כי
מייתי קרבן בשוגג, ki maysei korban be-shogeg, that I would have explained
since the word פתאום pitom can mean any point on that range,
I would have interpreted it to be the classic, what’s the classic
person who brings a קרבן? korban? A שוגג. shogeg. Normally if you’re
אונס ones you don’t, and if you’re מזיד meizid you don’t. If
you have no fault you don’t bring a קרבן, korban, and if
you are intentional, you’re, you know, your sin is too, is too
weighty for a קרבן. korban. The normal קרבן korban is only for
the middle, it’s only for שוגג. shogeg. So I would have interpreted
it in the classic way. So I would have said,
מידי דהוה אכל התורה כולה, midi de-hava a-kol ha-Torah kullah, like I
say on all other cases in the Torah that you only bring
a קרבן korban for שוגג. shogeg. אבל אונס ומזיד אימא לא, aval
ones u-meizid eima lo, by אונס ones and מזיד meizid I would
say not. כתב רחמנא פתא, ksav Rachmana pesa, so first it says
פתא, pesa, דשוגג הוא, de-shogeg hu, that’s שוגג. shogeg. לגלויי עלה דפתאום,
le-gilluyei alah de-pitom, and that reveals that the word פתאום pitom can’t
mean שוגג. shogeg. So what does פתאום pitom mean? דאונס ומזיד הוא,
de-ones u-meizid hu, that tells me the other two ends of the
spectrum.
ואפילו הכי חייביה רחמנא, ve-afillu hachi hiyveih Rachmana, and even so you
bring the קרבן. korban. And by the way, you can’t say, oh,
why didn’t it say I bring by מזיד meizid and then I
certainly bring by אונס, ones, or אונס ones and certainly bring by
מזיד? meizid? Because you could have said no, maybe if you’re מזיד
meizid you bring because you have guilt, and but maybe אונס ones
you have no guilt you don’t have to bring. Or the opposite,
if you have אונס ones you bring because at least you don’t
have guilt, real guilt. But if you’re מזיד meizid and intentional, you
don’t, you don’t merit the כפרה kapparah of a קרבן. korban. So
it has to tell me everything across the range. Even if you’re
completely blameless, even if you’re completely at fault, you still bring it.
And part of the reason this is probably true by a נזיר
nazir is the נזיר's nazir's קרבן korban that he brings when he
becomes טמא tamei might not be so much the sense of like
to atone for the guilt of the sin of becoming טמא, tamei,
but it’s sort of part of the process of, you know, of
like we learned before, part of the process of ending the נזירות
neziros of טומאה tumah and beginning the next נזירות neziros of טהרה.
taharah. So it’s part of the idea of like, you know, of
this changing of the state and not much atoning for the sin.
Or maybe another way of saying it and we talked already about
the idea of a חטאת, chatas, whether it’s about personal blame and
fault versus it about the metaphysical reality that a sin has been
done. So here there’s a metaphysical reality that a נזירות neziros has
been violated, and maybe that’s what needs to be addressed and, you
know, counteracted by the קרבן. korban. So the idea of personal guilt
and fault, אונס, ones, מזיד, meizid, שוגג shogeg doesn’t matter. There’s the
idea that the נזירות neziros has been violated and that needs to
be rectified through the bringing of the קרבן. korban. Okay, so that
is the issue now of two cases that you bring even מזיד,
meizid, and one of those נזיר nazir even by an אונס ones
is the שפחה shifchah and the נזיר. nazir. Now we have, we
have two more left on the list. So let’s see the other
two.
שבועת עדות. shvuas eidus. Now these two are easy, they’re, this is
like explicit in the פסוק. pasuk. מנלן דתנו רבנן דכולה נאמר ונעלם
וכאן לא נאמר ונעלם, menalan de-sanu rabbanan de-kullah ne'emar ve-ne'elam ve-chan lo
ne'emar ve-ne'elam,
לחייב על המזיד כשוגג. le-hayyev al ha-meizid ke-shogeg. It should be מזיד
meizid like שוגג. shogeg. Meaning, in ויקרא, Vayikra, and then we’re going
to get back to this of course because this is also the
category of עולה ויורד, oleh ve-yored, which is the next listing in
the, in the משנה. mishnah. It speaks about what do you bring
a קרבן korban of חטאת chatas that it’s a variable cost. And
that’s ויקרא ה. Vayikra hey. So here are the examples of this
עולה ויורד oleh ve-yored based on your ability to afford. So here’s
what it
says, ונפש כי תחטא ושמעה קול אלה והוא עד או ראה או
ידע ואם לא יגיד ונשא עונו. ve-nefesh ki secheta ve-shama kol alah
ve-hu eid o ra'ah o yada ve-im lo yagid ve-nasa avono. So
he swears falsely that he doesn’t know testimony, then he has to
bear his sin. Okay, so that’s swearing falsely about testimony. Notice it
does not say ונעלם ממנו, ve-ne'elam mimmennu, it was hidden from him,
he was an accident. Just says he swore falsely. Then it says,
או נפש אשר תגע בכל דבר טמא או בנבלת חיה טמאה או
בנבלת בהמה טמאה או בנבלת שרץ טמא ונעלם ממנו והוא טמא ואשם.
o nefesh asher tiga be-chol davar tamei o be-nivlas hayyah teme'ah o
be-nivlas behemah teme'ah o be-nivlas sheretz tamei ve-ne'elam mimmennu ve-hu tamei ve-ashem.
When it speaks about being טמא tamei and entering into the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash or eating קדשים, kodashim, which is another case of
עולה ויורד, oleh ve-yored, it says that it was hidden from you,
it was unintentional. And then it says, או נפש כי תשבע לבטא
בשפתים להרע או להיטיב לכל אשר יבטא האדם בשבועה ונעלם ממנו. o
nefesh ki sishava levatei bi-sfatayim le-hara o le-heitiv le-chol asher yevatei ha-adam
bi-shvuah ve-ne'elam mimmennu.
You took an oath to do something and it was hidden from
you, you forgot about it and you transgressed your oath. So transgressing
an oath or being טמא tamei and entering, eating the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash or eating a קרבן, korban, it says ונעלם, ve-ne'elam, you’re
a שוגג. shogeg. But swearing falsely about testimony, it doesn’t say that
word. And the last, and then it says, והיה כי יאשם לאחת
מאלה והתודה אשר חטא, ve-hayah ki ye'esham le-achas me-elleh ve-hisvaddah asher hata,
then it speaks about bringing your קרבן korban which is the variable
cost קרבן. korban. So of that, those, that’s a קרבן עולה ויורד,
korban oleh ve-yored, and one of those, one of these it did
not say that ונעלם, ve-ne'elam, so... That one about swearing falsely about
testimony, you bring even if you are intentional.
So maybe it's only if you're intentional.
No, it doesn't say. No reason to limit it to that.
Okay, so that's and it doesn't say בנעלם, b'ne'elam, which means it
was unintentional. This one it doesn't, which
means it could be intentional. No, it means that it doesn't matter
whether it's intentional or not. Because if it's not a criterion, then
it doesn't matter. Okay, it's not a criterion of the opposite. Alright,
so that's that. That is about שבועת העדות. shvuat ha'edut. Now we
go on, ושבועת הפקדון, ushvuat hapikadon, swearing falsely about having a having
an object by you for safe-keeping. מנלן? minalan? יליף תח תח משבועת
העדות. yalif tach tach mishvuat ha'edut.
Because it speaks about by שבועת הפקדון, ushvuat hapikadon, it speaks also
of one sins, it uses the phrase תחטא, techeta, and we learn
it out from the word by שבועת העדות, shvuat ha'edut, and we
learn that that is even if somebody does it intentionally. Okay, so
now I'm just fine.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so that's
in terms of the four that you bring even if you are
intentional. Now we move on to lists of five. חמישה מביאים קרבן
אחד על עבירות הרבה. chamisha mevi'im korban echad al aveirot harbeh.
One קרבן korban for many sins, and our משנה Mishnah mentioned two,
we'll mention more in the next משנה. Mishnah. So normally it's one
one קרבן korban for one sin, here you can bring one קרבן
korban for multiple. קתני הבא על שפחה פעמים הרבה. katani haba al
shifcha pe'amim harbeh.
So the first one is the first two are two that we
had in the other list as well, that if a person has
sex with a שפחה shifcha that is quasi-married, so even if it's
multiple times. מנלן? minalan? Where do you know it? דתנו רבנן. detanu
rabanan. וכפר עליו הכהן באיל האשם על חטאתו אשר חטא. vechiper alav
hakohen be'eil ha'asham al chatato asher chata.
So for the sin that he has sinned, that's a little redundant.
ללמד שמביא קרבן אחד על עבירות הרבה. lelamed shemevi korban echad al
aveirot harbeh. One קרבן korban for multiple sins, even multiple sins, one
קרבן korban is enough. ונסלח לו מחטאתו אשר חטא. venislach lo mechatato
asher chata.
Then again it says the sin that he has sinned, that's again
redundant. לעשות מזיד כשוגג. la'asot mezid keshogeg. So that's what we talked
about earlier, that all types of sin, even a willful sin. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says והא קרא כי כתיב במזיד כתיב.
veha kra ki ktiv bemezid ktiv. One minute. It said that sounds
like we assume that you bring the קרבן korban for שוגג shogeg
and we need the פסוק pasuk to include even intentional. But the
גמרא Gemara says actually פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim by the
sin with the שפחה shifcha is when it's a willful sin. How
do you know the פשט pshat is when it's a willful sin?
It's because it says
because basically because so the גמרא Gemara doesn't actually say here, but
רש"י Rashi explains because the גמרא Gemara learned out from the fact
that it says בקרת תהיה, bikoret tihyeh, there shall be an investigation,
that חז"ל Chazal learn out that that means that there are lashes,
there are מלקות malkot for this. That's a very bizarre sin or
punishment for this case of the שפחה חרופה. shifcha charufa. Besides that
it is multiple sins you get one punishment, also it's a case
where you get both lashes and a קרבן. korban. Because normally it
would be lashes for מזיד, mezid, קרבן korban for שוגג, shogeg, here
you get both. And they learn out lashes from the פסוק pasuk
of בקרת תהיה bikoret tihyeh and in another place the גמרא Gemara
learns out that that's referring to lashes. Okay, and therefore we know
that you only give you never give lashes בשוגג. beshogeg. קרבן korban
may be sometimes במזיד, bemezid, sometimes בשוגג, beshogeg, but lashes are only
במזיד. bemezid. So the גמרא Gemara says look, if there are lashes
here, the standard case is מזיד. mezid. So you don't need the
so the חידוש chidush is not that you bring a קרבן korban
by מזיד, mezid, that's what we're talking about, מזיד. mezid. So the
גמרא Gemara says okay, fine. So the גמרא Gemara says like this
where are we? אלא אימא לעשות שוגג כמזיד. ela eima la'asot shogeg
kemezid. Fine. So you're right. So it's not telling you here so
you're right, we assume the פסוק pasuk is talking about מזיד mezid
because that's the idea of lashes and it says קרבן, korban, it's
telling you קרבן korban is by מזיד. mezid. So when it says
מחטאתו אשר חטא, mechatato asher chata, that's telling you not only מזיד,
mezid, which is the simple sense of the פסוק, pasuk, but even
שוגג. shogeg. Even things that are not the simple case of the
פסוק, pasuk, even שוגג. shogeg. At the end of the point, it's
still the same הלכה, halacha, which is that for this sin of
the שפחה חרופה, shifcha charufa, you bring a קרבן korban whether you're
שוגג shogeg or מזיד. mezid. The only point that the גמרא Gemara
said is that where do I start? If I'm starting by focusing
on קרבן, korban, I assume it's שוגג shogeg and I need to
tell me, oh, not only like a classic קרבן שוגג, korban shogeg,
even מזיד. mezid. But if I start with the case of שפחה
חרופה shifcha charufa and I realize you get lashes, then I start
with the idea that it's talking about a מזיד mezid case. So
it's a very bizarre case, it's מזיד, mezid, you get lashes and
a קרבן. korban. But I'm starting with the idea of מזיד. mezid.
And then I say not only מזיד, mezid, even שוגג, shogeg, not
lashes, but even שוגג shogeg brings a קרבן. korban. But either way
it is a very strange case that you bring a קרבן korban
for שוגג shogeg and מזיד mezid and that if you are מזיד
mezid you get both lashes and a קרבן. korban. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara goes on, it says like this. בעי מיניה
רבי חנינא טירנאה מרבי יוחנן.
ba'ei minei
rabi chanina tirna'ah merabi yochanan. So רבי חנינא טירנאה, Rabi Chanina Tirna'ah,
interesting name, asked from רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan the following question. הבא
על חמש שפחות חרופות. haba al chamesh shifchot charufot. How far do
we go to say that multiple sins of שפחה חרופה shifcha charufa
is only one קרבן? korban? Let's say the person had five five
times, five acts of sex with five different
שפחות חרופות. shifchot charufot. בהעלם אחד, be'he'elam echad, and it was in
one state of forgetfulness that he forgot it was forbidden I guess,
or whatever, he didn't forgot who they were. Anyway, מהו? mahu? What's
the הלכה? halacha? חייב על כל אחת ואחת, chayav al kol achat
ve'achat, do you have to bring separate קרבנות korbanot or אינו חייב
אלא אחת, eino chayav ela achat, or only one? אמר ליה, amar
lei, he said to him, חייב על כל אחת ואחת, chayav al
kol achat ve'achat, you bring separate
קרבנות. korbanot. מאי שנא מחמש העלמות בשפחה אחת? mai shna mechamesh he'elamot
beshifcha achat? So he said back to him, why is it different
if you forget five distinct times by the same woman? Normally the
הלכה halacha is five, even if you did the same sin five
times... If you remembered in between, it's multiple קרבנות. korbanot. So normally
you'd have multiple קרבנות, korbanot, but here the חידוש chiddush is only
one, even if he remembered between each act and then he forgot
again, and normally that would be five קרבנות, korbanot, here it's a
חידוש chiddush is only one. So if that's true, why not even
with five different women let it only be one? So אמר ליה,
amar lei, he said back to him, what's the forgetfulness? What? And
one state of forgetfulness, right. If it's one woman and five states
of forgetfulness or five women and one state of forgetfulness, he says
what's the difference? Okay, so אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back
to
him, אין שפחה אחת גופין מחולקין. ein shifcha achat gufin mecholakin. One
שפחה shifcha is still not different bodies. ה' שפחות, hei shifachot, five
שפחות shifachot are גופין מחולקין, gufin mecholakin, are different bodies. Which is,
and we remember this going back to something we talked about before,
this is a repeating theme in כריתות, Kritot, how many times do
you, how many קרבנות korbanot do you bring for multiple, for the
same sin multiple times and so on. And the גמרא Gemara always
understands that it is much more of a distinct act when it
involves different objects or different people rather than if it's basically the
same thing repeated. So even if you remember multiple times and forget
multiple times, if it's with the same person, it's basically all the
same thing, just different states of awareness. But if it's with different
people, those are fundamentally different and we do not say you bring
only one sin offering, there you will bring multiple sin offerings. ומנלן
דגבי שפחה גופין מחולקין? u'minalan degabei shifcha gufin mecholakin?
Where do I know that by the case of שפחה shifcha separate
people, bodies make a difference if, you know, once we have this
idea that you only bring once? אמר ליה, amar lei, לאו אמרת
גבי עריות? lav amart gabei arayot? ואישה לחלק על כל אישה ואישה.
ve'isha lechalek al kol isha ve'isha. What do you mean? Way back,
you know, in the beginning of the מסכת, masechet, not way back,
but anyway, in the beginning of the מסכת masechet we said the
word ואישה ve'isha is to tell you that if it's different women,
even if it's the same sin, like it's נדה niddah multiple times
or whatever multiple times, you know, nevertheless each woman makes it different
and it's a different קרבן. korban. גבי שפחה נמי כתיב, gabei shifcha
nami ktiv, so by שפחה shifcha
we also have a special פסוק. pasuk. אשר ישכב את אישה שכבת
זרע, asher yishkav et isha shichvat zera, that he sleeps with the
woman a sleeping of seed, והיא שפחה, ve'hi shifcha, and she is
a שפחה. shifcha. Why does it say אשר ישכב את שפחה? asher
yishkav et shifcha? Why does it say woman and she is a
שפחה? shifcha? So to tell you the extra word woman is to
tell you, or the extra word שפחה, shifcha, anyway, לחלק על כל
שפחה ושפחה. lechalek al kol shifcha veshifcha. איש שפחה ish shifcha is
distinct. So even on the one hand we say multiple times one
קרבן, korban, but we do say different people, different קרבנות. korbanot. Okay,
so that is one case of multiple קרבנות, korbanot, multiple sins one
קרבן korban is שפחה חרופה. shifcha charufa. And now we deal with
the case of נזיר. nazir. Both of these are on both lists,
the lists of מזיד meizid and שוגג shogeg and the lists of
multiple times. Which by the way points to this idea as I
was saying that it's not so much about the sin itself but
more about like the effects of the sin. So by the נזיר
nazir it's about like
violating, the fact that the נזירות nezirut has been violated and the
קרבן korban has to be brought to sort of rectify that and
start a new נזירות. nezirut. So if violated once, violated five times,
the result is still the same in terms of the נזירות. nezirut.
You have a violated נזירות, nezirut, so there's only one קרבן. korban.
So that idea what it points to, both of these ideas, that
מזיד meizid and שוגג shogeg doesn't matter, multiple times and single times
doesn't matter, is to less about the sin than about the result.
Now the question is how do you transfer that idea also to
the case of the שפחה shifcha in terms of the result? And
I have some thoughts about that but anyway now there's another, other
place in ש"ס Shas where it more develops the concept of שפחה
חרופה, shifcha charufa, so and we're behind in time, but I'll just,
I'll just indicate that I think that's the way to be thinking
about the way in which שפחה shifcha and נזיר nazir are the
same here, both it doesn't matter מזיד meizid or שוגג, shogeg, it
doesn't matter multiple times, it's because it's more about correcting the effect
of the act or addressing the effect of the act, not about
the sin per se. So let's take a look at the case
of the נזיר. nazir. נזיר שנטמא טומאות הרבה. nazir shenitma tumot harbeh.
מאן תנא? man tana? Who is this תנא? tana? אמר רב חסדא
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה היא דאמר נזירות דטהרה משביעי הוא דחיילי עליה.
amar Rav Chisda Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda hi de'amar nezirut detahara mishvi'i
hu dechaylei alei. ומשכחת לה כגון שנטמא בשביעי וחזר ונטמא בשביעי. u'mashkachat
lah kegon shenitma beshvi'i vechazar venitma beshvi'i. So the גמרא's Gemara question
is the following. You would have thought what it means is, here
I am, I'm a נזיר, nazir, I became טמא, tamei, I became
טמא tamei once, twice, three times, four times, I went five times
into a cemetery on the same day. Okay, now the, the גמרא
Gemara doesn't understand, that the גמרא Gemara takes for granted that that
would only be one קרבן, korban, because there, you know, once I've
violated my נזירות nezirut once, becoming טמא tamei again, you know, it's
already been violated, my נזירות, nezirut, it's not even really that impactful.
Okay, so what the גמרא Gemara understands that the real חידוש chiddush
is not that I went multiple times into the cemetery on the
same day, but that I then started a נזירות nezirut again and
started a נזירות דטהרה nezirut detahara and then went again into a
cemetery and again violated a distinct נזירות דטהרה. nezirut detahara. So that
you would say maybe that's separate, right? Because the first case was
like the obvious case I was referring to. I might have sinned
five times, but it's only been one נזירות nezirut that has been
violated. So then it's obvious, one נזירות nezirut is violated, one קרבן
korban to fix it up, even if I personally sinned five times.
But the גמרא Gemara thinks it's even a bigger state, that even
if I started my נזירות... nezirut... again and I violated a new
one again and a new one again, it's only one קרבן. korban.
You mean after you brought all the קרבנות korbanos and did all...
No, no, no, no, before you start a new נזירות. nezirus. So
that's going to be the question. So the question is, well then
why would it only be one קרבן? korban? I only start my
new נזירות nezirus after I've brought my קרבן. korban. Okay, or even
if it's not after I brought my קרבן, korban, at least after
I'm חייב chayav in my קרבן.
korban. So then when I violate again, it should be a new
obligation of a קרבן. korban.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara has to now describe the case.
Let's take a look. In the first case, if there was different
acts, would it still be one קרבן? korban? Like you went to
a... Yes, but the גמרא... Gemara... Yes, but the גמרא Gemara takes
all of that for granted. Meaning the way I tried to explain
why multiple times and שוגג shogeg and מזיד mezid doesn't matter is
because it's all one thing that happened, the נזירות nezirus has been
violated. So the גמרא Gemara takes that like completely for granted and
it goes... assumes that we're talking about even if it's through distinct
acts. The גמרא Gemara understands that we're talking about... Yes, different days.
But the גמרא Gemara understands we're making a bigger חידוש, chiddush, even
if a new נזירות nezirus has been violated. So it wants to
understand, well how did that happen? Didn't you already become obligated in
the קרבן? korban? So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says, it's רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה דאמר נזירות
דטהרה משביעי הוא דחייבא ליה.
Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Yehuda
de'amar nezirus
detahara mishvi hu dechayiva lei.
Your new נזירות nezirus begins on day seven.
Right, when a נזיר nazir becomes טמא, tamei,
he goes through a seven-day purification process like anybody who becomes טמא
למת, tamei lemeis, and he brings his קרבן korban on day eight.
When does his new נזירות nezirus begin? On day seven when he
becomes טהור, tahor, on day eight when he has to bring his
קרבן? korban? I'm sorry, wait, what happens day seven? He becomes טהור,
tahor, the seven-day purification process until he's טמא. tamei. And then his
קרבנות... korbanos... Yes, his קרבנות korbanos is day eight. So when does
his new נזירות nezirus begin? On day seven when he becomes טהור,
tahor, day eight when he has to bring his קרבנות. korbanos. So
this is רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Yehuda that
says it begins on day seven. ומשכחת לה כגון שנטמא בשביעי, Umishkachas
lah kegon shenitma beshvi, so he became טמא tamei on day seven
from his previous טומאה, tumah, he started his new נזירות, nezirus, and
now on that day itself he became טמא. tamei. וחזר ונטמא בשביעי,
Vechazar venitma beshvi, and then it happened again. So at the same
day he began his נזירות nezirus before the eighth when he would
become חייב chayav in a קרבן, korban, that day he began his
נזירות nezirus on day seven and he became טמא. tamei. So his
new טומאה tumah occurred before he became obligated in his קרבן korban
from the earlier נזירות. nezirus. So therefore, וכיון דלא יצא שעה הראויה
להקריב בה קרבן, vecheivan delo yata sha'ah haruyah lehakariv bah korban, since
he never entered into a time when he was obligated in a
קרבן korban before he had become טמא tamei again, so אינו חייב
אלא קרבן אחד, eino chayav ela korban echad, it's only one קרבן.
korban. דאי רבי, De'i Rabbi, if it was רבי, Rabbi, כיון דאמר
רבי נזירות דטהרה עד שמיני לא חייבא ליה, keivan de'amar Rabbi nezirus
detahara ad shemini lo chayiva lei, רבי Rabbi says your new נזירות
nezirus does not begin until day eight. Well, as soon as the
day breaks of day eight, you're obligated in your קרבן. korban. So
then when you begin now your new נזירות, nezirus, you can't just
say oh one קרבן korban for everything, you already became obligated in
your קרבן korban before you began your new נזירות. nezirus. So אי
נטמא בשביעי, i' nitma beshvi, if you became טמא tamei on שביעי
shevi וחזר ונטמא בשביעי, vechazar venitma beshvi, כולה טומאה אריכתא היא. kulei
tumah arichta hi. That's not a חידוש chiddush at all. Then it's
only one נזירות nezirus that you're constantly being מטמא, mitamei, right? Because
he says your new נזירות nezirus didn't begin till day eight. So
if you became טמא tamei five times on day three or four
or five or six or seven, so you're just multiple times violating
one נזירות. nezirus. So for the גמרא Gemara that's not a חידוש
chiddush at all. That's obvious that it's only going to be one
קרבן. korban. אי נטמא בשמיני, I' nitma beshmini, and if you became
טמא tamei on the eighth day וחזר ונטמא בשמיני, vechazar venitma beshmini,
כיון דיצא שעה הראויה להקריב קרבן, keivan deyatzah sha'ah haruyah lehakariv korban,
so once day eight began and your new נזירות nezirus began, well
at the moment your new נזירות nezirus began you also already became
obligated in a קרבן. korban. So now if you are מטמא mitamei
this, it's going to be a separate קרבן. korban. מחייב על כל
אחת ואחת, Mechayev al kol achas ve'achas, so you have to bring
on each one. אלא שמע מינה רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Ela shema
mina Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Yehuda, you see it's רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Yehuda. So therefore, according to the גמרא,
Gemara, the חידוש chiddush here, and this really brings the
נזירות nezirus case, right?
The נזירות nezirus case is like interesting midpoint between the קרבן korban
that's brought for sin and a קרבן korban that's brought for טהרה,
tahara, right? Because the idea of the קרבן korban for the נזיר
nazir is you wrap up the נזירות nezirus of טומאה, tumah, you
begin the נזירות nezirus of טהרה, tahara, and so on. So is
that like a case of, you know, the גמרא, Gemara, the משנה,
Mishnah, excuse me... Right, so it's somewhere like midpoint about those two.
So in the next משנה Mishnah we're going to see that by
the case of a יולדת, yoledes, that's also a case the גמרא
Gemara is going to say you bring one קרבן korban for multiple
times, and there clearly it's not about multiple sins, there it's about
multiple childbirths, right? And there it's clearly about the purification process. So
here, this is a question, how do we think about the קרבן
korban of a נזירות nezirus of טומאה? tumah? Is that about the
sin of being טמא? tamei? Well the גמרא Gemara said אונס ones
or מזיד, mezid, the sin doesn't really matter. Or is it about
somehow like the childbirth case, part of the cleansing of the previous
process and the beginning of a new one? So the גמרא Gemara
understands if it's about multiple times you became טמא tamei for the
same נזירות, nezirus, then it's like obvious, it's all just one wrapping
up of one process even if it's multiple sins. The חידוש chiddush
here is even if it's multiple נזירות, neziruses,
there are ways you can bring one קרבן. korban. What is that?
Is it before you became obligated in the קרבן korban for the
previous one, you started your new נזירות nezirus and then you became
טמא tamei again? And then because of that, although they're distinct נזירות,
neziruses, there never was a moment in that previous process where you
became obligated in your קרבן korban yet, so one קרבן korban at
the end will satisfy both. Only under that opinion that it begins
on day seven. Correct. And the גמרא... Gemara... ומאי רבי יוסי בר
יהודה? U'mai Rabbi Yosi bar Yehuda? Where do we see this debate?
דתניא: De'tanya: וקדש את ראשו ביום ההוא. Ve'kidash et rosho bayom hahu.
This talks about when the נזיר Nazir ends his previous נזירות Nezirut
and begins his new one. So he begins his new נזירות Nezirut
on that day. What's that day? ביום הבאת קרבנותיו, Byom havat korbanotav,
דברי רבי. divrei Rabbi. Rabbi says it's the day you bring your
קרבנות, korbanot, day eight, that's when you begin your new נזירות. Nezirut.
רבי יוסי בר יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yosi bar Yehuda omer, ביום תגלחתו.
byom tiglachto. No, the day you shave, on day seven, that's when
you begin your new... that's when your new נזירות Nezirut begins. Okay,
so again, the idea that if I became טמא tamei five times
while I was a נזיר, Nazir, at the end, if I looked
at it as a... as a sin, then the idea that I
only bring one חטאת chatat is a חידוש. chiddush. But if I
look at it as like cleansing the previous and beginning the new
one, then it's not a חידוש, chiddush, you know, that I bring
only one thing. There's only one נזירות Nezirut I violated. So the
גמרא Gemara takes for granted that's how we look at it. And
therefore, when it says multiple, one sin for multiple times, it's not
five times for one נזירות, Nezirut, it's five distinct נזירות. Neziruses. But
the only way you get that without it leading to five distinct
קרבנות korbanot is that the new נזירות Nezirut begins before I become
obligated yet in the קרבן korban from the previous. This is discussed
by one נזיר, Nazir, but how can you say anything other than
eight days? It's all in the פסוק pasuk by eight days. ביום
השמיני יביא שתי תורים Byom hashmini yavi shtei torim and so on
and so forth. וקדש את ראשו ביום ההוא. Ve'kidash et rosho bayom
hahu. It's in the same פסוק. pasuk. How can you say... I
understand. Okay, רבי Rabbi is פשט. pshat. What can I... what can
I say? What if you say he became טמא tamei the evening
before the eighth day? No, because according to רבי, Rabbi, it's still
ביום ההוא. bayom hahu. It would only still begin on the daybreak
itself, not on the... not on the evening before. And that... and
that immediate daybreak would also obligate him in the קרבן. korban. Exactly,
they both come at the same time. Okay, so that is two.
So one was the case of the שפחה חרופה. shifcha charufa. The
next was the נזיר טמא, Nazir tamei, which is, I would say,
somewhat midpoint between an idea of sin, but certainly from the גמרא's
Gemara understanding, it's pushing it much more to this idea of the
טהרה tahara process. And certainly, I would also say פשט pshat in
the פסוקים, psukim, it's a way of sort of ending the טומאה
tumah and beginning the טהרה. tahara. And now we go on to
the list of other cases where you bring multiple for one... one
for multiple, I should say. המקנא לאשתו על ידי אנשים הרבה. Hamakane
l'ishto al yedei anashim harbeh. Let's say a man was jealous of
his wife and told her, right, don't... you know, don't be in
private with that man, and she goes in private with that man.
That's the פרשה parsha in the תורה Torah of סוטה. Sotah. And
what happens if that... if that happens and there's testimony that she
went in private and all of that? So she's brought to the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and she's made to drink this water, the
מי המרים המאררים, mei hamarim hamarerim, and she brings a קרבן, korban,
right? She brings a מנחת סוטה. minchas Sotah. She brings a מנחה,
mincha, סוטה, Sotah, excuse me, מנחת סוטה. minchas Sotah. She brings a
מנחה mincha in that process. Now, let's say this was for multiple
suspicions, right? He said don't be in private with that man, and
don't be in private with that man, and she... and all of
those things happened, and he brings her to the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, you know, once for all of those events, not separate times.
So in that case, she would only bring one מנחה. mincha. You
would not do five separate, you know, five separate acts and five
separate מנחות, minchos, you would do it all as one thing. ומצורע
שנתנגע נגעים הרבה, U'metzora shenitnaga nega'im harbeh, and a מצורע metzora that
became... that had many spots of leprosy. So he became... and now
we're also going to see what that means. I mean, if it
just means that I... you know, are those distinct times? I mean,
if I'm a מצורע metzora and I get another sign of צרעת
tzara'as and another sign of צרעת, tzara'as, you would say fine, it's
all just like one thing, right? Just wait till it's all done.
So again, we're going to see here whether... and how we make
those into sort of distinct things. Okay? So at the end of
the process of the מצורע metzora purification, so you bring only one
קרבן korban even if they are separate צרעת. tzara'ases. הביא ציפורין. Hevi
tziporin. Now, let's say he does his birds, right? The purification of
מצורע metzora is you bring two birds, you שחט shacht one, you
take the other one into the blood and so on. So let's
say you bring the birds ונתנגע, venitnaga, and then you became a
מצורע metzora again, he became a מצורע metzora again. לא עלו לו.
Lo alu lo. It didn't count עד שיביא חטאתו, ad sheyavi chataso,
until you bring the חטאת, chatat, because in addition to the birds,
which is part of the purification, not a קרבן, korban, there's a
קרבן חטאת. korban chatat. This is a different day, right? Yeah. רבי
יהודה אומר, עד שיביא אשמו, rabbi yehuda omer ad sheyavi ashamo. until
he brings his אשם. asham. So that's not at all clear what
that means. We'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. But let's first focus.
So now again, you'll notice these two cases, right, are much more
about purification than they are about sin. So the idea of one
for multiple, other than the שפחה חרופה shifcha charufa and even there
I would think you can talk in those terms, but we're not
going to discuss that right now. But anyway, all of these work
much better if they're not focused on the act of sin, but
on the result and the cleansing and the purification. So we spoke
about נזיר, Nazir, now we have the idea of sort of the
woman who is suspected. It's not like her being in private was
a sin and it needs a קרבן korban to atone for her
violating her husband and for being in private. The whole purpose here
is to address the suspicion and to address her status and so
on. So it's all sort of one thing in terms of addressing
the suspicion and not about sort of separate distinct acts that were
sins that needed to be atoned for. So where is the cleansing?
Well, I understand. Meaning, it's not exactly... they're not all about cleansing.
I don't think that the שפחה חרופה shifcha charufa is about the
cleansing either. But my point... so that was a little bit too
narrow. But my point here is that if you focus on the
act acts and somehow the acts were wrong and needed to be
atoned for, then you would say multiple acts, multiple sins. So it's
much less about the act and much more about the result. So
you're right, some of them it's the result of טומאה tuma and
cleansing, like the case of צרעת tzara'at and the case of נזיר.
nazir. Others, like the case of סוטה, sota, I would say the
result is the cloud of suspicion that needs to be addressed. And
that's sort of what we're focusing on, not the acts of going
into private. Why is it so hard to address that? That, okay,
that is a much bigger question, you know, which is when we
learn פרשת סוטה parshat sota or מסכת סוטה, masechet sota, right, this
idea that it's the woman at fault and not the husband and
all of those issues. So I can't address that now, okay? But
right now what I want to focus on is, I promise you,
when we get to מסכת סוטה, masechet sota, we will talk about
it. But right now I just want to focus on the idea
that it's not about the sin of going in private, it's about
the suspicion. And therefore it's one thing that ultimately is addressed and
therefore multiple sort of, you know, violating her husband or going into
private, whatever, is only one קרבן korban or one thing because it's
all about the suspicion in the end. Okay, so let's take a
look at the גמרא. gemara. מנלן? menalan? How do you know by
סוטה sota it's only one קרבן korban even for multiple things? דכתיב,
dechtiv, the verse says, זאת תורת הקנאת, zot torat hakenaot, this is
the תורה torah for jealousy. תורה אחת לקנויין הרבה. torah achat lekinuyin
harbe. So קנאת kenaot is sort of like a קנאת, kenaot, you
know, it's the plural. Plural, like jealousies, and one תורה torah for
multiple jealousies. Even if it's multiple different jealousies, it's going to be
one one act and one thing. מצורע שנטמא בנגעים הרבה. metzora shenitma
benegaim harbe. So that was very quick with the סוטה. sota. See,
the גמרא gemara also didn't want to get into it, Rivka. But
now we go on to, okay, מצורע metzora multiple times. Now how
are you going to have multiple צרעת? tzara'at?
What does that mean? I mean, why don't we just call it
one big צרעת? tzara'at? Let's take a look. מנלן? menalan? דכתיב, dechtiv,
זאת תורת המצורע, zot torat hametzora, this is the law of the
מצורע. metzora. תורה אחת למצורעים הרבה. torah achat lemetzoraim harbe. One תורה
torah for multiple cases of זאת תורת המצורע. zot torat hametzora.
I know, but it's emphasizing more תורה.
torah. Like תורה torah is like a category, like a whole category,
like a law, you know, one general rule for everything.
But exact—anyway, the specific cases are not so clear, so let's continue
to read in the גמרא. gemara.
Okay, so the גמרא gemara says like this: הביא צפורים ונטמא לא
עלו לו עד
שיביא חטאתו.
hevi tziporim venitma lo alu lo
ad sheyavi chatato.
רבי יהודה אומר עד שיביא אשמו. Rabbi Yehuda omer ad sheyavi ashamo.
So if she brings the birds, it's not done until you bring
the חטאת chatat or the אשם. asham. So the גמרא gemara says,
והאמרת אין מביא אלא קרבן אחד? veha'amarta ein mevi ela korban echad?
But one minute, you said that you only bring one קרבן, korban,
which means that somehow this sounds like—let's—the way it sounds is, right,
if we think about the analogy to the נזירות nezirut case, it
sounds like you brought your birds, so you're טהור tahor again. You
didn't yet bring your קרבן, korban, and then you became a מצורע
metzora again. Meaning, what would be the case of one קרבן korban
for multiple צרעת? tzara'at? How do you have multiple צרעת? tzara'at? Not
like you're a מצורע metzora now and in the middle of being
מצורע metzora you get other spots. That's not multiple, that's all one
state of being מצורע. metzora. But no, you were a מצורע, metzora,
you did the cleansing with the birds, and now before you brought
your קרבן, korban, which is the end of the process, you became
a מצורע metzora again. So after you were טהור tahor but had
not yet brought your קרבן, korban, you became a מצורע metzora again,
and then again and again and again. So similar to the case
of the נזיר, nazir, you became a מצורע metzora distinct times after
you became טהור, tahor, but it's only one קרבן korban at the
end. Okay, that's presumably what we're talking about. But then the גמרא
gemara says, but the משנה mishna says that it doesn't count until
you bring your חטאת, chatat, which somehow sounds like—like, you know, it's—somehow
sounds like you—you know, it doesn't help you to be only one
קרבן. korban. So what does this mean? So the גמרא gemara says,
חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. chasuri mechasra vehachi katani. No, it's missing some
words here, how it's to read. הביא צפורים, hevi tziporim, you brought
your birds, ונטמא, venitma, and then you became a מצורע metzora again,
אין מביא אלא קרבן אחד. ein mevi ela korban echad. You only
bring one קרבן. korban. That's פשט pshat in the first half of
the משנה. mishna. Separate, if you became cleansed, טהור, tahor, צרעת tzara'at
again, but you haven't brought your קרבן, korban, צרעת tzara'at again, at
the end of the whole thing, even if it's multiple times, only
one קרבן. korban. But for a separate הלכה, halacha, ולאקבועי בעניות ובעשירות
לא מיקבע עד שיביא חטאת. ule'akvuei be'aniyut uve'ashirut lo mikba ad sheyavi
chatat. To determine whether you're poor or rich, that's determined at the
moment of bringing the חטאת. chatat. So something completely different, right? What
does this mean? So if you take a look in the תורה,
torah, right? So it says, because one of the cases also that's
an עולה ויורד, oleh veyored, which we're going to get to, is
the קרבן korban of a מצורע, metzora, that it's variable value. So
here's what the תורה torah says at the beginning of מצורע, metzora,
right? Most of the מצורע metzora is talked about in תזריע. tazria.
The beginning of מצורע metzora is זאת תהיה תורת המצורע ביום טהרתו.
zot tihye torat hametzora beyom taharato. What happens when you finish it?
So it says, what do you do? So it says, so it
says, you wait—you—you take these two birds, right? ושני תולעת ואזוב וטבל
אותם ואת הצפור החיה בדם הצפור השחוטה וגו' והזה על המטהר מן
הצרעת שבע פעמים וטהרו ושלח את הצפור החיה על פני השדה וכבס
המטהר את בגדיו וגלח את כל שערו ורחץ במים וטהר ואחר יבוא
אל המחנה וישב מחוץ לאהלו שבעת ימים. ushni tolaat ve'ezov vetaval otam
ve'et hatzipor hachaya bedam hatzipor hashchuta vego' vehiza al hamitaher min hatzara'at
sheva pe'amim vetiharo veshilach et hatzipor hachaya al pnei hasade vechibes hamitaher
et begadav vegilach et kol se'aro verachatz bamayim vetaher ve'achar yavo el
hamachane veyashev michutz le'ohalo shivat yamim. So you wait seven days after
this purification. והיה ביום השביעי יגלח את כל שערו את ראשו ואת
זקנו ואת גבות עיניו, vehaya bayom hashvi'i yegalach et kol se'aro et
rosho ve'et zekano ve'et gabot einav, you do the whole shaving, וכבס
את בגדיו ורחץ את בשרו במים וטהר. vechibes et begadav verachatz et
besaro bamayim vetaher. So you do the bird thing, seven days you're
טהור. tahor. So again, it's like the case of נזיר, nazir, right?
Wait, wait. No, וביום השמיני, ubayom hashmini, no, וביום השמיני ubayom hashmini
is... And then on day eight, now on ביום השמיני day eight
you bring the קרבן korban that ends the whole thing. Okay, so
like we discussed before, you became טהור tahor on day seven. Let's
say he then became a מצורע metzora again, then he became טהור,
tahor, מצורע metzora again. Since you never yet became obligated in a
קרבן, korban, right, because it wasn't yet day eight, presumably that's a
similar type of a scenario, then finally when you when you finish
this whole thing, you'll bring one קרבן korban and everything. Like we
talked about the case of a נזיר. nazir. You became טהור, tahor,
you became טמא tamei again before you became obligated in the קרבן,
korban, it'll be one set at the end. What do you do
though on day eight? וביום השמיני יקח שני כבשים תמימים וכבשה אחת
בת שנתה תמימה ושלושה עשרונים Uvayom hashemini yikach shnei kvasim tmimim vechivsa
achat bat shnata tmima ushlosha esronim etc. סולת solet etc. והעמיד הכהן
המטהר את האיש המטהר אותם לפני ה' פתח אהל מועד vehe'emid hakohen
hametaher et ha'ish hametaher otam lifnei Hashem petach ohel moed and you
bring this whole קרבן. korban. And then there's this אשם asham that
does this whole thing about the using of the blood of the
אשם asham to finish the purification process on day eight. Now, the
פסוק pasuk says at the end of day eight, וכפר עליו הכהן
וטהר. vechiper alav hakohen vetaher. I know, so it's the end of
the purification process, okay? It's like... So it's been two days essentially?
Yes. Now the point is that there is a variable, there are
three things here that are brought. What is brought? So it says
you bring כבש אחד לאשם, keves echad le'asham, okay, one sheep for
an אשם asham and that's the blood of that is used with
oil as part of a purification process. And then it says that
you also bring, where is it? You have three sheep. So one
is an אשם asham and one is ועשה הכהן את החטאת, ve'asa
hakohen et hachatat, one is a חטאת, chatat, and then there's an
עולה. olah. There's a חטאת chatat and an עולה olah and an
אשם. asham. Okay, now what happens if you can't afford it? So
it says ואם דל הוא ואין ידו משגת, ve'im dal hu ve'ein
yado maseget, then ולקח כבש אחד אשם, velakach keves echad asham, so
the lamb that's an אשם asham remains the same, לכפר עליו, lechaper
alav, but ועשרון סולת בלול בשמן למנחה ולוג שמן, ve'isaron solet balul
bashemen lemincha velog shamen, but then you also bring ושתי תורים או
שני בני יונה אשר תשיג ידו ואחד חטאת ואחד עולה. ushtei torim
o shnei bnei yona asher tasig yado ve'echad chatat ve'echad ola. So
if you can't afford it, then the sheep that's an אשם asham
that's part of the purification process is fixed, but the חטאת chatat
and the עולה, olah, rather than being two sheep, could be two
birds. So one of the questions here is, what stage do you
determine how rich or poor I am, whether it has to be
two sheep or two birds for the חטאת chatat and the עולה?
olah? So that's the גמרא Gemara says is the next part of
the משנה. Mishnah. So let's keep on going. It says like this:
ולקבוע בעניות ובעשירות לא מקבע, ulekavo'a be'aniyut uve'ashirut lo mikva, to determine
whether you're poor or rich, that's not determined עד שיביא חטאת, ad
sheyavi chatat, when you bring your חטאת. chatat. Now again, it's a
little ironic because your חטאת chatat is determined whether you're rich and
poor, but basically it says, let's say I don't know, when I
brought my אשם asham I was poor and then before I brought
my חטאת chatat I won the lottery. Okay, or the reverse, you
know, between bringing the אשם asham and the חטאת... chatat... They're all
brought on the same day, right? I know, things can happen in
a minute. Between bringing the חטאת chatat and the אשם, asham, right,
my company went bankrupt. So at what moment do you say, ah,
since you were rich here or poor here, that's determined. So one
opinion is you go by the חטאת. chatat. When you're actually bringing
the חטאת, chatat, which is based on whether you're rich or poor,
at that moment we say are you rich or poor right now?
Right now, based on whether you're rich or poor, will determine whether
you bring a lamb or a bird. Okay? They're all brought in
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. All right, fine. Anyway, so עד שיביא
חטאת. ad sheyavi chatat. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer, עד שיביא
אשמו. ad sheyavi ashamo, No, when you bring the אשם, asham, which
is maybe makes a little more sense because the אשם asham is
always fixed as a lamb, so when you bring the אשם, asham,
when that determines then how the next two קרבנות korbanot are going
to be. If at the time of the אשם asham you were
rich or poor, that will determine whether the next two קרבנות korbanot
are sheep or are birds. Okay, תנן התם, tenan hatam, we learned
over there, המצורע שהביא אשמו והעשיר, hametzora shehevi ashamo vehe'ashir, you brought
your אשם asham which is a lamb which is always fixed and
then you won the lottery. הכל הולך אחר חטאת. hakol holech achar
chatat. Since by you have not yet brought your חטאת chatat and
now you're coming to bring your חטאת chatat and you're rich, now
you bring the full value, now you bring it as a rich
person and you're going to bring it from the lamb. דברי רבי
שמעון, divrei Rabbi Shimon, that's Rabbi Shimon says. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi
Yehuda omer, and here you see by the way it's the exact
same תנאים, Tannaim, which makes sense that the גמרא Gemara is saying
that's what our משנה Mishnah was referring to. רבי יהודה אומר הכל
הולך אחר האשם. Rabbi Yehuda omer hakol holech achar ha'asham. No, since
by the אשם asham moment you were poor, therefore even now that
you're rich, you still bring the poor person's korban and you bring
the birds. And the same would be true in the reverse. תניא,
tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, Baraita, רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר
הכל הולך אחר ציפורים. Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer hakol holech achar
tziporim. No, I push it back even further. I go what happened
on the previous day when you were being purified with the birds,
actually yes, seven days before, you know, seven days ago when the
purification process began, that at that moment we determine whether you were
defined as rich or poor for this הלכה. halacha. So אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב שלושה מקרא אחד דרשו. amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav
shlosha mikra echad darshu. They all base themselves on one פסוק. pasuk.
אשר לא תשיג ידו בטהרתו. asher lo tasig yado betaharato. It says
this will be the law that you bring birds instead of lambs
for the חטאת chatat and the עולה olah for somebody who cannot
afford it for his purification. So what does it mean for his
purification? רבי שמעון סבר דבר המכפרו. Rabbi Shimon savar davar hamachapro. So
Rabbi Shimon says that you go after the חטאת, chatat, it is
the thing that atones for you, that's your purification. רבי יהודה סבר
דבר המכשירו. Rabbi Yehuda savar davar hamachshiro. רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says
no, here טהרה tahara means something that really, really cleanses you, meaning
that makes you fit for being a non-מצורע, metzora, and that's the
אשם. asham. That's really טהרתו, taharato, it's not about atonement, it's not
about sin, it's about cleansing, and therefore you go by the אשם.
asham. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר דבר הגורם לו טהרה. Rebbe Elazar
ben Yaakov omer davar hagorem lo tahara. It says טהרתו. taharato. It's
not the thing that finishes the purification process, which is the אשם,
asham, it's the thing that begins the purification process, which is the,
which is the birds. ומאי נינהו צפורים. Umai ninhu tzipparim. So this
again goes back to the larger theme, which is which קרבנות korbanot
are for the sake of purification, which are for the sake of
sin, right? And in general here, like a lot of these things
we're saying is about purification, but by the, by the מצורע metzora
it's interesting because he does multiple קרבנות. korbanot. You don't just have
one thing like a חטאת, chatas, or we want to say like
by the יולדת, yoledes, that's about purification. You have a חטאת chatas
and an אשם. asham. So is maybe we'll say that the אשם
asham is about the cleansing and it was used in the cleansing
process and that's about the purification, and the חטאת chatas is about
the sin, right? So that is some of these different opinions. So
פסוק pasuk says טהרה. tahara. So does טהרה tahara where טהרה tahara
begins, the birds, where טהרה tahara ends, the אשם, asham, or maybe
טהרה tahara here doesn't just mean purification, it somehow means atonement and
it actually focuses us on the חטאת chatas and not on these
other sins. But again, these are the sort of recurring themes here
about which of these קרבנות korbanot are about sin and which of
them are about purification. וזה החטאים וזה הטהורים. V'zeh hachata'im v'zeh hatoharim.
Right, well actually that is true though as well, by יום כפור
Yom Kippur as well. How much is it about sort of personal
guilt and how much is it about the טומאה tumah of the
מקדש Mikdash and being, you know, sort of the metaphysical טומאה? tumah?
And I think that's a general issue by the חטאת, chatas, you
know, we tend to focus חטאת chatas on the sense of personal
sin, but that's actually a little bit more, you know, kind of,
so to say, more with אשם, asham, although even אשם asham is
not a clearly defined category. Okay, so those are now cases, so
far we did four of the five cases. The שפחה, shifcha, which
is not so clear what that's about. We have the נזיר, nazir,
multiple טומאות, tumos, distinct multiple sequential טומאות, tumos, I should say. The
מצורע, metzora, sequential טומאות, tumos, but in some ways because they were
not interrupted yet, it didn't get to the stage yet of bringing
the קרבן, korban, it was on the day seven and so on,
therefore it's only going to be one קרבן korban at the end.
Multiple sequential but טומאות tumos but one קרבן. korban. And the case
of the סוטה, sotah, which is also one thing because again it's
not, as I would say, act-focused, it's about the suspicion. Now we
get to the last case, which is, that's four out of the
five, now we get to the last case, which is a case
of a יולדת, yoledes, childbirth, which we had before also clearly about
the idea of טהרה. tahara. We're going to get a case about
multiple sequential childbirths, which only one קרבן korban at the end. Let's
take a look. Have we had this one already? We sort of
did. But anyway. האשה שילדה ולדות הרבה. Ha'ishah sheyaldah veladot harbeh. A
woman that gave birth to many children, many births, I should say.
Now the, yes, sequential, but in order to have it again, the
point is that if she, when does a woman bring her קרבן?
korban? So if it's a male, at day 41, right? She's טמא
tamei seven days, 33 days which she bleeds she's טהור, tahor, a
40-day process, day 41 she brings her קרבן. korban. By a female,
it's 14 and 66, day 81. Now, based on the similar assumptions
we've made before, as soon as you hit the day you're obligated
in a קרבן, korban, if you become pregnant again and give birth
again, it's going to be a separate קרבן. korban. The only way
it's going to be one קרבן korban for multiple times is if
the other state began, process began, before you became obligated in a
קרבן. korban. So we can only have this if we're dealing about
miscarriage, right? Because if we were dealing about just natural childbirth, that's
obviously going to happen, you know, much, you know, if she's gave
birth, if we need to have another birth within 80 days of
giving birth, it can only be a case of a miscarriage. So
we're going to draw scenarios, and now miscarriage if it's after 40
days of the fetal development, it's considered a לידה leidah and you
bring a קרבן. korban. So a woman gave birth to a female,
and we're going to talk about case of female because that gives
us 80 days to work with, not 40 days. Gave birth to
a female. She was טמא tamei 14 days. So she wasn't having
sex with her husband. Then she had sex, she became pregnant. The
fetus developed for 40 days. So now we're on day, you know,
54 or something, right? And then she miscarries, that's another birth that
she has now had that came before she became obligated in the
קרבן, korban, before she hit day 81. And if that scenario happens
multiple times. With a fetus that's 40 days old, how do you
tell if it's a male or female? Well, you can't. But the
first birth could have been a full-term birth. First of all, how
long would you have to miscarriage? Oh, so if you don't know,
then you have to be מחמיר machmir both ways. Okay, but if
it's a, meaning, you'd be 14 days of טמא tamei like a
female, but only טהור tahor until day 40 like a male. Okay,
anyway, we're not getting into. Anyway, so if you do that scene
multiple times, you can have multiple births, but because each birth took
place before the, or miscarriage took place before the day 81 hit,
before the קרבן korban hit, it would be one קרבן korban at
the end. Okay, so let's take a look. האשה. Ha'ishah. she miscarried
within the 80 days, so נקבה nekeiva another female, so you somehow
knew it was a female, and so that gives you another 80
days to count from now. חזרה והפילה בתוך שמונים נקבה hazra ve-hipila
be-toch shemonim nekeiva and again within the 80 days another miscarriage of
a female. So all those cases, no matter how many times that's
repeated, that would only be one קרבן korban because the next birth
happened before she became obligated in a קרבן. korban. Or והמפלת תאומים.
ve-ha-mapelet te'omim. The גמרא Gemara mentions, I don't know if this is
true, but the גמרא Gemara mentions that a woman could have, who
had twins, could have a case where the second child came out
days after the first child. I don't know if that's at all
possible. Anyway, so that type of case, it's similar to the idea
of becoming pregnant again because if it was, if the child actually
came out on a different day, it would be like another birth,
not like a continuation of the same birth. So if a woman
basically had a, you know, child on one day and then the
second child came out a week later or two weeks later or
three weeks later, again I don't know if it's at all possible.
Anyway, it's similar to becoming pregnant again and miscarrying, and all this
came before בן שמונה לבן שמונה, ben shemonah le-ben shemonah, right? Yeah.
Okay, right. But anyway, it's not as interesting in terms of, yes,
right, it could be. That's well, I guess that's true, but the
גמרא Gemara is going to have even more radical cases than that.
Anyway, all those cases, although it's multiple births, it would only be
one, it would only be one קרבן. korban. Although those cases are
more obvious, especially if it's like Michael's case, a simple issue of
like before and after sunset. Okay, so let's take a look. Anyway,
so רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, so that's a case about
one קרבן. korban. Now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has a more, has
a different opinion. רבי יהודה אומר מביאה על הראשון ואינה מביאה על
השני, מביאה על השלישי ואינה מביאה על הרביעי. Rabbi Yehuda omer mevia
al ha-rishon ve-eina mevia al ha-sheni, mevia al ha-shlishi ve-eina mevia al
ha-revii. You bring on one, three, and five, you don't bring on
two, four, and six. Why? What's the logic? If you have multiple
births, you bring on the odd ones, not on the even ones.
Why? Because what he says is the logic, if I had a
thing I would show you, but anyway, here let's try to use
this visualization. This is birth number one, okay? You had the baby
here, then you had this, this is like, you know, the 80
days, right? So this is birth number one. And somewhere within the
80 days, there was another miscarriage, right, towards the end of the
80 days, right? And then in the second case, towards the end
of this 80 days, there was another miscarriage, right? That's sort of
how the גמרא Gemara is explaining it. So the חכמים Chachamim say,
oh, so basically it's like the birth continues all the way and
only at the end of the entire process when you get to
a day, it's one קרבן korban for everything. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says no. He says look, this birth took place within the period
of this 80 days. So this birth is part of this birth,
and therefore it's one קרבן. korban. But this is not part of
this birth. This number three did not take place within the 80-day
span of number one. Okay? So what we'll say is we'll say
two is an extension of one, and this is its own new
thing, and this is a new thing, and therefore three is its
own קרבן, korban, and three and four is its own קרבן, korban,
and four and five are its own, and five and six are
its own קרבן, korban, and so on. That's what he says. It's
not that it keeps on, it doesn't daisy chain, it doesn't keep
on stretching out, right? It's just that each one that's within the
other one gets, and once two gets incorporated in one, three can't
get incorporated in two because now two and one are considered basically
like a form of one. And since three is not part of
one, three has to be its own thing. Okay, so that's what
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. I heard a Guinness Book of World
Records was 84 days. How much? 84. 84 days between two babies
coming out? The first one must not have been, the first one
must have been miscarried, right? The first one live birth? Really? 84
days? How's that? I don't know. All right, let's take a look.
One could be a preemie. That's what I said, but 84 days.
But does the womb, I guess, would the cervix close again? It
must. That's what I didn't know, if the cervix closed afterwards. It'd
be more than just a cervix being open to give birth. I
guess. All right, wow. All right, let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. מנא לן? Mena lan? Oh my god, we are now
a full דף daf behind. מנא לן? Mena lan? Let's at least
finish the bottom of that. How do you know this, that this
is only, that this is one קרבן korban at the end? דתני
תנא קמיה דרב ששת, De-tani tana kamei de-Rav Sheshet, זאת תורת היולדת,
Zot torat ha-yoledet, this is the תורה, Torah, again the word תורה,
Torah, for the יולדת, yoledet, לזכר ולנקבה, le-zachar u-le-nekeiva, male or female.
So it's one law for multiple, you know, one thing for even
multiple cases. מלמד שמביאה קרבן אחד על ולדות הרבה. Melamed she-mevia korban
echad al veladot harbeh. One thing even for multiple births. יכול אף
על הלידה ועל הזיבה? Yachol af al ha-leida ve-al ha-ziva? Maybe even
if she both gave birth and became a זבה, zava, which is
also a distinct טומאה tumah and requires a distinct קרבן, korban, maybe
it's only one קרבן? korban? תלמוד לומר זאת. Talmud lomar zot. No,
this, meaning it's not in all cases it's only one, it's limited.
קתני, Katani, so now the גמרא Gemara says what type of question
was that? קתני יכול על הלידה ועל הזיבה אינה מביאה אלא קרבן
אחד? Katani yachol al ha-leida ve-al ha-ziva eina mevia ela korban echad?
Maybe for childbirth and for זיבה ziva it's one קרבן? korban? These
are completely different things. So אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, if that's your
הוה אמינא, hava amina, why not say אכלה דם וילדה הכי נמי
דמביאה קרבן אחד? achla dam ve-yalda hachi nami de-mevia korban echad? Let's
say she, you know, ate חמץ בפסח chametz be-Pesach and gave birth,
maybe one קרבן? korban? I mean they're completely different, right? They're both
טומאות tumot that relate to women, but they're completely different and they're
completely different קרבנות. korbanot. Why should I think that one counts for
two? Right, one counts for multiple childbirths, why could I think all
of a sudden think oh and it also counts for totally different
things? What type of question is that? אלא אימא ella eima
so the גמרא Gemara says no, rather, אימא הכי. eima hachi. יכול
על הלידה שלפני מלאת על הלידה שלאחר מלאת. yachol al haleidah shelifnei
melot al haleidah shele'achar melot. תלמוד לומר זאת. talmud lomar zot. Meaning
what's the real case we want to say? If you say one
for many, you want to say well maybe it's not only many
when it overlaps. Maybe even if the next birth is on day
81, right, and then the next one remember that was the בית
הלל בית שמאי Beit Hillel Beit Shammai some of the cases the
night before 81. Maybe if they're completely distinct, maybe one for many?
Like the case of שפחה חרופה shifcha charufa when they were completely
distinct. And it says no, here it's only because they're an extension
and an overlap. If they're completely distinct, then it's not. So again,
the only case is the שפחה חרופה shifcha charufa is where it's
really completely distinct. But these cases about נזיר, nazir, יולדת, yoledet, and
מצורע, metzora, where it's much more about the purification process, there if
it really is distinct and you already became obligated in a קרבן,
korban, then you have to do a separate קרבן. korban. It's only
when it somehow overlaps and it's seen as an extension of like
of the טומאה, tumah, of the
process, that's when it's one קרבן korban for multiple things. Okay, let's
just finish to the bottom of the page. הפילה בתוך שמונים, hipila
betoch shemonim, so if it's within day 80, so now we're going
to describe the difference between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the חכמים.
Chachamim. כשתמצא לומר, keshetimtza lomar, if you want you can say, meaning
לדברי רבי יהודה ולד ראשון גורם ומולד ראשון מונה. lidvrei Rabbi Yehuda
vlad rishon gorem umivlad rishon moneh. According to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
we focus on the first birth. And therefore the first birth, the
second birth gets incorporated into the first. And then the third remains
distinct. But the way we sort of define the process is we
say the second birth is part of the first. And because the
second is part of the first, the third is left alone. It's
not part of the first, it's a new thing. That's what רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. לדברי חכמים ולד שני גורם ומולד שני מונה.
lidvrei Chachamim vlad sheni gorem umivlad sheni moneh. According to the חכמים,
Chachamim, they don't focus on the first and have to incorporate things
in the first, they basically focus on the end of the process.
And they basically say that by, you know, it's not ולד שני,
vlad sheni, it means the last one. It means that, you know,
it's not like everything was the first and everything has to be
considered part of the first. It's that, you know, as long as
we have not yet got to a period where you bring a
קרבן, korban, it's all one big extended thing. It's all defined by
the end. You don't have to incorporate it in the beginning. Since
you don't yet have an endpoint, it hasn't ended. It's not that
you have to sort of incorporate it into the beginning. So the
גמרא Gemara says, כשתמצא לומר, keshetimtza lomar, if you want you could
say, פשיטא הכי, peshita hachi, of course that's what they're debating about.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, במפלת תאומים איצטריכא ליה, bemapeles teomim
itztricha lei, we're telling you that even in the case of twins.
סלקא דעתך אמינא במפלת תאומים מודה רבי יהודה לרבנן. salka da'atach amina
bemapeles teomim modeh Rabbi Yehuda lerabanan. Since רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
saying that the idea of incorporating it into the first, maybe he
would say in a case of twins, or let's say it was
triplets or something like that, maybe he would say there since clearly
it was all one pregnancy, even if you had these cases of
84 days spacing or whatever, you know, maybe there he would say
that even if it's not within the first 80 days, since it's
all really one pregnancy, there he would agree it's one long process.
It's not all about incorporating it into the first. So if you
had a case of triplets, you understand, right, and each one sequential,
maybe he would say there that three is part of one. So
maybe he would agree. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that no,
that he always says that even in a case of triplets and
one long process, the only way we can join them is saying
that the, you know, that something that came after is incorporated in
the thing before. But the thing before is what defines the parameters.
And anything not within 80 days, the first 80 days, is a
distinct thing. As opposed to חכמים Chachamim that focus on the end
and they say if you haven't actually got to an endpoint yet,
they all still continue. And we will continue with this tomorrow.